[Music]
hello and welcome to episode 5.5 i'm
calling this one um because i said in
the last episode that the next
episode would be
looking at the chests in the chest
system but before i do that i just want
to go back through the code and do a bit
of a code review and start commenting so
um
hopefully going forward if anyone has
any issues they can you know the code
will make a bit more sense and i'm going
to release this kind of
mid-week so it's um this isn't going to
replace the
chest video that will come out when it
was supposed to come out and that will
be episode 6. so if we go over to our
inventory item data script i'm just
going to leave i'm just going to type
three slashes and do a summary at the
top of this script so
this is um
a scriptable
object that defines what an item is in
our game it could be
inherited from
to have
branched versions of items
for example
potions and equipment
because they would all have different
stats so you know we've defined that
inventory item data at the very top
level they'll have an id a display name
a description an icon and a maximum
stack size you could have like a
monetary value as well so you could do
a public and like gold value so how much
it's worth and then you could derive a
new script from this and have a potion
object or have a
sword object or some armor
so you could have multiple classes that
inherit from inventory item data and
they would still all plug in to our
inventory system because it have the
kind of base stuff that we need for
example the icon and the max stack size
i mean this is all self-explanatory
these are all named kind of
self-explanatory so i think that's fine
let's kind of move up to
inventory slot so this is a
reference to the data of what makes up
an item
this is the current stack size
of the slot so how many of the data
how many of the data do we have
these are the public um getters for
these
so this is a constructor to make a
slot of stuff in it so constructor
to make a
occupied
inventory slot
this is the constructor that makes a
blank slot so constructor to
make a
make an empty
inventory slot
and my self-explanatory book clears the
slot
so this one assigns an item to an
inventory slot that's already been made
because all inventory slots are created
at the start and they're empty so we can
actually assign an item directly to
the slot so assigns and item to the slot
so here we're seeing
does the slot already contain the item
we're trying to assign to it so
does the
slot contain the same item
and we can add
to the stack if so so add to stack
if so
and else if it's not the same item
we're trying to assign a different item
to the slot
and let's overwrite the data
reset the stack size and add
how many of the item that we're trying
to assign to
the new slot
so else overwrite slot
with the inventory slot that we're
passing in
we've also got update inventory slot
which assigns the data and the amount
directly it doesn't reset them
i can't remember exactly where we're
using this but i'm pretty sure we are
um but just updates slot
directly
now this code you know some of this may
end up being redundant and we can always
go through at the end and try and like
do a bit of refactor and tidy everything
up because i
i do think
i've doubled up on some kind of code
systems here but it works at the minute
so that's fine
and we've got our room left in stack
function so um this is checking
[Music]
would there
be enough room in the stack
for the amount
we're trying to add
so if we're trying to add
two
to the stack
if the current stack size plus the two
that we're trying to add is less than or
equal to the maximum stack size then
there is enough room left in stack
and if there's not we'll can return
false
so actually maybe we could rename this
to enough room left in stack
because that's what we're actually
checking we're not
room left in stack makes it seem like we
are trying to get the amount remaining
but we're not always trying to do that
we're just checking is there enough room
left in the stack
to take this amount let's just call that
enough room left in stack i mean this is
self-explanatory you add to the stack
and remove to the stack here we're not
taking into account the item data's
maximum stack size which
could be a
bad thing
but in the inventory system
we are we're taking that into account
before we actually add it to the stack
so that's why we don't ever go over the
maximum stack size because we are
checking that here
um before we add it to the inventory in
the inventory system
so you know we could check and return a
ball
if
it can't but that we're kind of that's
kind of what's
happening here we're doing enough room
left in stack and then we're there is
enough room adding it to the stack and
we're checking that here
so this is fine stack size plus amount
like it won't ever go above the maximum
stack size so here we've um split stack
again it's kind of self-explanatory but
we're saying
here
um
is there enough to split
is there
enough to actually
split because we can't have 0.5 of
something we can only have one if
something is the maximum so we need to
make sure that uh the stack size is
more than one
so if not we'll return false and nothing
will happen
if there is we'll just half the stack
get half
the stack
we'll remove from stack
as this will minus the half stack from
this current inventory slot
then we'll just return a new inventory
slot with the half stack so we can
assign that where we need to assign it
so creates um
a copy of this slot with
half the stack size
so hopefully that kind of makes sense
so the next kind of thing up in our kind
of hierarchy is the inventory system
which it contains all of the slot so
let's go over to our inventory system so
this is the
list of inventory slots that kind of you
know makes sense itself which will have
a size that we pass in
here so this is the constructor
that sets the amount of slots
and then depending what size we pass in
we just do a loop and add to this list
empty slots like
so we pass in 10 we're gonna make 10
empty slots and add it to our list
then we've got our attitude inventory
which is going to check which again is
kind of self-explanatory
um
it checks whether the item exists in the
inventory so does it contain the item
and it will pass back out a list of all
of the slots that contain the item and
then for each of the slots in that list
we're going to check is there enough
room left in the stack for the amount
that we want to add and then if there is
enough room left in the stack then we
add it to the stack and we just return
true and invoke our event on inventory
slot change so the ui can update there
isn't enough room left in the stack
nothing
happens
so if there isn't enough room left in
this stack then if we come out of this
if loop and we check do we have a free
slot so an empty slot
if we do have a free slot and we pass
back out the the slot that is empty then
we update that ui the free slots
inventory slot with the amount that we
want to add and then we call our on
inventory slot changed event so actually
here
we probably will need to check um
for the maximum stack size because
realistically we shouldn't ever pick up
more than you know the stack sizes
amount but we do need to check for that
so what we can do is we can just check
this so if
free slot enough room
left in stack
with the amount to add
then if there is we'll update the
inventory slot
of the free slot and then call our
onslaught changed event and we'll just
return false if neither of these are
true so the inventory is full okay so we
actually need to rename this to enough
room left in stack there's a bit of an
issue there
let's just see will that get rid of that
yeah that should get rid of that error
so let's just make sure this uh free
slot system works now we've changed it
which it didn't so let's just double
check what's going on there
so we need to need to check that item
data is actually
valid
so if item data
is not equal
to null
actually we can just get rid of that and
say if i'm data is not equal to null and
stack size
plus amount to add is less than or equal
to the item date as max stack size
return true
actually if it's null
we want to say it has enough room in the
stack as well so
if it's either null or it's not null
and the stack size is um you know this
this meets the requirement then return
true else return false so let's just try
that so there you go that's still
working so this gets the first available
slot checks whether that slot has enough
room in it and if it does it'll add it
to the inventory it's just a bit of a
fail save to make sure it never goes
over the um
stack size and we could also
you know here in the future um
add implementation
to only
take what can fill the stack
and check for another free slot
to put the remainder in
for example in minecraft you can put
multiple items on the ground you can
have like a stack of
you can have multiple apples and you'll
pick them up it'll fill up the stack
then i'll put whatever's left into a new
stack so we can that's where we can add
the implementation there if we want to
currently we'll just check the free slot
and if the free slot doesn't have enough
room left in its stack nothing will
happen it'll just stay on the ground and
we won't pick up the item so here we're
checking
um does
do any of our slots
have the item
to add in them
if they do
get a list
of all of them
and if they do return
true
if not return
false
writing a list of all of the slots that
equal the item data that we're trying to
add to our inventory i'm going to put
them in a list if that list
isn't null so if it has found them then
return true and if it is null we'll just
return false and this is just
get the first
free slot so the first slot that has
no data in it the date is null
so just get the first free slot
okay so that's this inventory slot
looked at let's go up to inventory
holder and this is very simple
all it does is it creates a new
inventory system based on the size that
we've given it
and in the next few videos we're going
to spin this out into a player inventory
and a chest inventory
and they'll inherit from inventory
holder and they'll have their own kind
of uh
systems in place
but for now i think this is kind of you
know self-explanatory
so let's look at our mouse item data
script which is the one that when we
click on a slot we
update this mouse slot
so the item sprite count is all kind of
self explanatory the assigned inventory
slot that's fine as well and to be safe
we can do get and private sets on these
because we don't need to set them
externally we'll always set them by
updating
slot on
we'll actually use this method to update
the slot so this is going to assign the
item to our inventory slot
it's going to set the sprite text and
color to
whatever we've assigned if it has an
item
follow the mouse so
if
has an item
follow the mouse
position
as a bit of um
to do here we're going to add the
ability to
uh use a controller and it'll follow the
controller around the screen instead of
the mouse and it'll go from slot to slot
so to do
add controller support
we'll do that towards the end though
um
so if we do have some item data we're
gonna set the current position
to the mouse's current position
and if we press the left button and
we're not over any ui we'll clear the
slot
here we can have
a to-do and this is going to drop the
item on the ground
instead of deleting it
if you want to do that we can go ahead
and do that um but for now we'll just
delete the item we'll click outside and
it'll it'll disappear and be deleted all
this clear slot is doing is it's just
clearing our assigned inventory slot and
then resetting the values to kind of the
defaults and hiding hiding it so that
the mouse item data won't be seen and
here's that code that i got off stack
overflow to just show whether the mouse
position is currently
um
over ui
so when we click we're doing a raycast
from the mouse position
and we create a list of everything that
we hit
that's on the ui layer because we're
using the event system
which responds to the ui
and if this list is um
greater than zero
then we've obviously hit some ui
elements so we won't delete the
uh item that's on the mouse
but if it is zero then we haven't hit
any ui so we're clicking into the world
so let's delete the item on the mouse
and we've already looked at our
inventory item data let's go and look at
the pickup
so this has got a pickup radius and some
item data that's all self-explanatory
collider self-explanatory we're getting
a collider we're sending trigger to true
and setting the radius to pick up radius
now on our trigger enter we're just
looking whether the thing that hit us
has um
an inventory script if it doesn't we're
just going to return nothing will happen
if it does we'll try and add ourselves
to the system's inventory that's
successful we we add it to the inventory
and that that that happens then we'll
destroy the object and if not nothing
will happen and we'll just stay on the
ground waiting for on trigger enter to
be called again to check again once we
implement the player inventory and chest
inventory scripts we'll have to change
this up slightly but for now this this
is fine so over on our inventory display
script so this is just a reference to
our mouse item data this is the object
in the game world this inventory system
is the inventory system that we are
trying to display we set this in our
static inventory display by getting it
from the inventory holder
and we make a dictionary of
imagery slot ui elements and their kind
of system counterparts in our slot
dictionary
so
pair up the ui slots with the system
slots in a dictionary
and then we've got a getter for the
inventory system and this slot
dictionary in case we need them
we've got protected virtual void start
in case we need to do anything later on
in the start method and we can override
that in our
static inventory display which inherits
from this class
we've got an abstract void assigned
slots which um we don't do here
because it's going to be different based
on
the kind of child classes
so the this is implemented
in child classes
update slot is a method that's called on
our inventory system when something
changes on the inventory we pass in the
slot that's updated and then we search
the slot dictionary
for that inventory slot
and if it is that slot we update the key
which is the ui slot we'll update that
slots ui
we've said here so slot dot value is the
under the hood system slot
the key is the ui representation
so the system says in slot
3 system slot 3 we've updated we've
picked something up it will update the
ui slot that's paired with the system
slot in our dictionary okay slot clicked
and i think i covered this quite well in
the last few in the last video we did
when we we built this out this is
already pre or commented but i'll just
go through it again so if the player is
holding the shift key which we've hard
coded here um if you wanted to allow the
player to change this you'd have to use
the input system to do that
and create like an input action asset
for example and here we're saying um
does the clicked ui slot have some data
on it we're checking to see whether the
item doesn't so
um
does the
clicked slot have
item data
and
does the mouse
have no item data
if the player is holding the shift key
then we'll split the stack
else
we will
pick up
the item in the clicked slot
if we're not tranish uh split the stack
and if we can't split the stack because
there's only one item in the stack then
we will um
we'll just pick up the item instead
now here we're checking
does the
click slot not have an item in it and
does the mouse
have an item in it because if it does
then we can just place the item into the
click slot
and then we're going to check so both
slots have an item
so we need to decide what to do
so here we're checking is it the same
item and is there enough room in the
stack to take everything from the mouse
if there is um both items are the same
so we're going to combine
combine the stacks
we're going to place the mouse item onto
the click slot here we're seeing is it
the same item and if it is and there's
not enough room left in the stack so if
it's if there was enough it'd do this if
it's not enough room left in the stack
then we need to find out how much room
there is left
and kind of account for that so
if it's less than one we'll swap the
items because the stack's full and if
the slot isn't at max
then we'll take what we need from the
mouse inventory and add that to the
click slot and just leave
however much we haven't taken still on
the mouse
and if it's not the same item so if
we're trying to put a potato on a tomato
it's not the same item we can't combine
the stacks so let's just swap them so
we'll assign the tomato to the mouse and
put the potato where the tomato was and
then swap slots we are cloning our
inventory slot
from the mouse
because we're going to overwrite it and
we need a copy of it so we can put it
back in so here we need to make a copy
of the mouse's inventory item because
we're then going to clear it and update
it with what's on the click slot
and then we need
because it's cleared that's why we've
cloned it so then we can
put that information back into the
clicked ui slot
so we'll clear that we'll make sure the
ui slots being cleared we'll assign the
new clone slot and then we'll update the
ui slots elements to kind of show
the system slot now on the front end
uh we'll come back to inventory slot ui
let's just stick with the inventory
display so this inherits from our
inventory display class which we've just
been through we're going to call base
start on an override did start just in
case like i said we want to call
anything in the inventory display start
and now here we're saying if our
inventory holder
isn't equal to null
and let's get the inventory system of
our
inventory holder
and subscribed the on inventory slot
changed
um
subscribe to the on inventory slot
changed event and assign our update slot
function to that which is on our
inventory display
so that's uh
this here which is called when we add in
an item to our retrieve from the ground
so we're going to subscribe to that
method
i'm going to debug.log a warning here if
this isn't the case
just so we know what the problem is that
there was no inventory assigned to the
object
and then we can just assign our
inventory slot systems
which is this abstract method which i've
said is implemented in the child classes
so that's implemented here so it's
public override void assign slot
it takes in an inventory to display
which is our inventory system
it creates a new dictionary
in memory from that slot dictionary that
we've we've decided we need because this
is a static display it needs the right
amount of slots for the um
inventory size so here we're saying if
the slot stop length which is an array
of our prefab ui slots
if that's not the same as the inventory
size then we'll just debug.log
to say that the slots are out of sync
but if that's not the case then we will
go into a loop and we'll add to our
dictionary that we've just made we'll
add the slot and its corresponding
system slot
and we'll initialize
this um
and we'll initialize the ui slot
with its counterpart um
inventory slot from the system so in our
init function you can see that that just
assigns the inventory slot and then
updates the ui slot
um just in case you know if we if we're
loading the game and something's already
in our inventory system
then it'll update it'll it'll show that
straight away it won't just be a blank
ui slot so finally over on our inventory
slot ui
we've got that init function like i just
mentioned um but this is kind of like
the mouse item data so there's the
sprite the count and an inventory slot
which has been assigned
it's also got a button element on it
and then here we're just getting that
button
we're subscribing our on ui slot click
event to that
and we've also got a variable called
parent display which gets the inventory
display component on our transform dot
parent so the inventory slot uis are
childed to the parent display which is
inventory display that could be static
or it could be the dynamic inventory
display but we're just getting the top
level inventory display cause that's all
we kind of care about
and the reason that we only care about
that is because when the slots clicked
we're gonna all we're gonna do is access
our parent display slot clicked method
and pass ourselves into it
and that's on
inventorydisplay.cs that's not on the
static inventory display so other than
um in it we've just got update ui slot
and then we're going to update the ui
slot and pass in
a
inventory slot to display so we're going
to say if slot.itemdata isn't equal to
null then we're going to set our sprite
and the color to y and then we're going
to set the sax size and if it's over one
we'll set that and if it's zero we won't
display any number in the stack size
and if the data is null and if the
inventory slot is um
empty then we'll set the item count dot
text to
blank the
sprite invisible will null out the
sprite
then we've also just got a version of
that method that doesn't take an
inventory slot
and we call this when our assigned
inventory slot isn't equal to null so we
call this method and pass in
our assigned inventory slot and then
we've got clear slot which just um
clears out our assigned inventory slot
so it empties
it
clear slot it just sets it to null stack
size minus to one and it sets our item
sprite to null or color to null and our
text to just blank
i mean that's all pretty
self-explanatory so i'm not bothered to
leave comments on that okay the problem
i just know it's a problem we can't do
get private set here because if we do
that we can't set them in the inspector
so let's just get rid of that we didn't
need to do that anyways it's fine that
these are public if we wanted to have a
getter we could make them private and
serialize we can set them inspector
and then do what we're doing
here and just make a public property but
let's just reset that to not be get in
private set
and then actually in our mouse object
we'll have to reassign
our image
and our item count that was a silly
mistake on my part
but yeah so this is where we are at
that's all of the code in review
we can pick up everything
it'll add itself to
a stack if we move this to the end and
pick up more tomatoes it'll add it to
that one because it'll find it
that's full so it'll find the first free
slot so that's that's where we are
that's the end of episode 5.5 which was
the code review which was an extra kind
of lesson to go through and just to kind
of recap on all the code i hope that all
makes sense and i hope if you were
confused about anything previously that
that's kind of cleared up and you kind
of get it now as always leave a comment
below or join the discord server if you
want to um if you want help with
anything if you're watching these videos
as they're going up live the full um
series all the way through to the end is
currently available over on
patreon.com and so are packages from the
end of every um lesson i save out a
package with the scripts in that current
state so you can compare your code
with the code from that lesson if you
want to again they're over on patreon
which is linked in the description but
for now thanks for watching and i'll
catch you in the next one bye
you